<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About Me on Congo</title>
    <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About Me on Congo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my website. # I’m a doctor of philosophy, and work as a philosopher and critical disability theorist. Until recently, I was an Irish Research Council Government of Ireland Postgraduate Scholar in the School of Philosophy at University College Dublin.
My research falls within the tradition of critical disability studies, and also draws upon feminist philosophy, twentieth-century continental philosophy, biophilosophy, and philosophy of technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/archives/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/archives/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Vitae</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/cv/</guid>
      <description>Education # Degree Year(s) University College Dublin PhD in Philosophy (awarded with minor typographical corrections) 2013&amp;ndash;2021 Thesis Title: “Distributing Disability: Embodied Difference, Technology, and the Human”. MA in Philosophy (First Class) 2011&amp;ndash;2012 Thesis Title: “Rebellious Matter: Towards an Ontology of Embodied Difference”. Queen’s University Belfast BA (Hons) in Sociology and Politics (First Class) 2008&amp;ndash;2011 Dissertation Title: “Live Flesh: Materiality, Subjectivity, Agency”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disability, Personhood, and Vulnerability</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-personhood-vulnerability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-personhood-vulnerability/</guid>
      <description>Presented at &amp;lsquo;Invited Speaker Seminar Series&amp;rsquo;, Nordic Network Gender Body Health / Imagining Technologies for Disability Futures 16 December 2021. This is a work in progress and not for citation.
Disability is a consistent topic of concern within philosophical ethics (including medical and applied ethics, and bioethics). In many cases, however, it is viewed as a misfortune, and an impediment to well-being.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disability and The Inhuman</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-inhuman/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-inhuman/</guid>
      <description>Presented at ‘The Inhuman Gaze and Perceiving Otherwise’, Centre Culturel Irlandais, Paris, France, 6-9 June 2018. This is a work in progress and not for citation.
A final version of this paper is published as “Disability and the Inhuman”, in Perception and the Inhuman Gaze: Perspectives from Philosophy, Phenomenology and the Sciences, edited by Anya Daly, James Jardine, Fred Cummins, and Dermot Moran, 298-307.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repealing the 8th Amendment need not erode disability rights</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/8th-amendment-disability-rights/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/8th-amendment-disability-rights/</guid>
      <description>In their arguments against repeal of the 8th Amendment of the Irish Constitution, the No campaign has used Down syndrome to suggest that this Amendment is necessary to protect disability rights. It isn’t.
First, the Love Both campaign website notes that government proposals contain no explicit ban upon abortion on grounds of disability diagnosis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disability, Technology, Time: The Technological Unconscious as an Unsafe Ground for Bodily Activity</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-technology-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-technology-time/</guid>
      <description>Presented at the Nordic Network Gender Body Health workshop &amp;lsquo;Interrogating Prostheses&amp;rsquo;, Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden, 15-16 May 2017. This is a work in progress and not for citation.
The main content of this paper is published as &amp;ldquo;Unsafe Ground: Technology, Habit, and the Enactment of Disability&amp;rdquo;. Women, Gender &amp;amp; Research 31, no.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disability and Prosthesis Beyond Utility and Function</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-and-prosthesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/disability-and-prosthesis/</guid>
      <description>Presented at Nordic Network Gender Body Health conference &amp;lsquo;Disability, Arts and Health&amp;rsquo;, Bergen University, Bergen, 1-2 September 2016.
Not for citation.
Introduction # Technologies are not mere external utilities, but are profoundly involved within human development. Explanation of such involvement takes various forms. Like natural and social artefacts, technologies have a historical development, and can acquire metaphysical baggage (Hui 2016).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Expression and The Structure of Behaviour</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/expression-structure-of-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/expression-structure-of-behavior/</guid>
      <description>Presented at &amp;lsquo;Workshop with Donald A. Landes on Merleau-Ponty and the Paradoxes of Expression&amp;rsquo;, University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland, 18 May 2016. This is a work in progress and not for citation.
This paper is part of a workshop with Donald A. Landes on his book Merleau-Ponty and the Paradoxes of Expression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atypical Morphology and the Normative Limits of Ability and Function</title>
      <link>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/normative-limits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jonathanpaulmitchell.com/posts/normative-limits/</guid>
      <description>Presented at &amp;lsquo;Theorizing the Body in Health and Medicine&amp;rsquo;, Maastricht University, Maastricht, Netherlands, 25-26 November 2015.
Not for citation.
Introduction # This paper largely concerns grounding concepts that inform medical and social theories of impairment. It discusses impairment in relation to normal function, including its identification as deviation from normal health.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
