<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Jonathan Paul Mitchell</title>
    <link>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Jonathan Paul Mitchell</description>
    <image>
      <url>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 12:25:28 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Disability, Personhood, and Vulnerability</title>
      <link>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/disability-personhood-and-vulnerability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/disability-personhood-and-vulnerability/</guid>
      <description>Disability is a consistent topic of concern within philosophical ethics (including medical and applied ethics, and bioethics). In many cases, however, it is viewed as a misfortune, and an impediment to well-being. This is because matters of the good human life turn on some criterion—rational autonomy, say, or personhood—that distinguishes good from bad lives. These specify certain properties or capacities that are purported to be essential to humans, and for a good life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disability and The Inhuman</title>
      <link>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/disability-and-the-inhuman/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/disability-and-the-inhuman/</guid>
      <description>When presented with the term ‘inhuman’, I was drawn to consider how certain ways of being become associated with the inhuman, how this association is involved in the constitution of what is taken as properly human, and the deleterious effects for those who become associated with the inhuman. I’m going to address these topics in three stages. First, I’ll briefly sketch how common understandings of disability might be thought of as ‘dehumanising’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repealing the 8th Amendment need not erode disability rights</title>
      <link>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/8th-amendment-disability-rights/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 12:25:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jonathanpaulmitchell.com/post/8th-amendment-disability-rights/</guid>
      <description>In their arguments against repeal of the 8th Amendment of the Irish Constitution, the No campaign has used Down syndrome to suggest that this Amendment is necessary to protect disability rights. It isn’t.
First, the Love Both campaign website notes that government proposals contain no explicit ban upon abortion on grounds of disability diagnosis. It infers from this that “babies with disabilities” and “babies with Down syndrome” are placed at “serious risk” (I won’t say much about this rhetorical strategy that conflates foetus with baby or child besides noting that a foetus is neither, and that you can read more about that here).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
